Guide to the Mary Coolidge Rentschler Collection 1793-2000 (bulk, 1875-1950) MS 2999
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Manuscripts and memorabilia
  - Subseries I.A. David Hill Coolidge Sr. (1833–1907) [DHC]
    Civic involvement is attested to by the twenty commission certificates spanning from 1858 to 1906. These include appointments as Justice of the Peace, master of Chancery, and Commissioner of Insolvency in Massachusetts, as well as Commissioner for the States of Maine and Michigan, and membership of the Board of Trustees of the Hospital Cottages for Children in Boston (Box Ovz-1 and Ovz-2). Coolidge's three scrapbooks are filled with press clippings of local civic news, as well as domestic and foreign affairs. For example: a report of the battle of Gettysburg; an electricity exhibition conceived of by Coolidge and George S. Hale; administration of Boston's City Hospital with an item petitioning admission of female students; judicial abuses in Italy (Box Man-1, Folder 4). Finally, letters he received from Congressman W. W. Warren in 1875 and 1876 indicate firsthand knowledge of Washington politics. The letters discuss currency and the gold standard, as well as impeachment, corruption, and electioneering (Box Man-2, Folder 7).
    The scrapbooks contain an eclectic group of materials. Aside from those previously mentioned, other items of interest include: a tiny and beautiful notebook of his scholastic record at his alma mater, Harvard University (Box Man-2, Folder 10); programs and press clippings concerning Arlington Street Unitarian Church to which he belonged (Box Man-2, Folder 15); a silk menu (Box Man-1, Folder 3); a handwritten poem to him on his seventeenth birthday, with miniscule photographs of women attached (Box Man-2, Folder 11); innumerable printed poems (Box Man-3, Folder 2), and a bill of safe passage for himself and R. C. Billings in the Civil War south (Box Man-1, Folder 4). (Billings became a very successful Boston businessman.)
    His diverse interests and the papers he chose to keep reflect a civic-minded and successful Bostonian and provide a wealth of information from which to create a family genealogy.
    - Promissory note and mortgage, 1793 February 20-1826 May 9 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Promissory note and mortgage, Milk Street property, David Hill, 1793-1796, and Indenture between Pratt & Hill, 1826, Boston, Massachusetts.
    - U.S. War Dept. Revolutionary claim, 1833 February 20 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Pension certificate of David Hill for service in American Revolution.
    - Commissions, 1857 September 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate for DHC to practice law in Massachusetts (dates do not correspond).
    - Commissions, 1858 February 9 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC Justice of the Peace, County of Suffolk, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1858 October 1-2 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC commissioner for the state of Maine, October 1-2, 1858 (dates do not correspond).
    - Commissions, 1859 March 24 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC a commissioner (in Massachusetts) for the state of Michigan.
    - Certificate of substitute furnished during rebellion, 1860-1865, Boston, MA, 1864 June 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Commissions of David Hill Coolidge (1859-1927): "certificate of subsitute furnished during rebellion, 1860-1865." Certificate appointing Boulden Haney? as substitute for DHC in the Civil War.
    - Commissions, 1865 January 31 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1865 December 6 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC commissioner of insolvency, County of Suffolk, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1868 November 20 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1871 November 24 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1872 January 26 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1874 November 21 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1877 November 23 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1879 January 9 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1879 January 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Confirmation and notice of appointment of DHC as a Master in Chancery, County of Suffolk, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1879 January 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC as a Master of Chancery, County of Suffolk, Massachusetts.
    - Stock certificate for 100 shares in Brayton Petroleum Engine Co., CT, 1880 February 26 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Commissions of David Hill Coolidge (1859-1927): DHC stock certificate for 100 shares in the Brayton Petroleum Engine Company, Connecticut.
    - Commissions, 1884 January 11 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1885 December 23 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1889 January 16 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Notice of appointment of DHC as a Master of Chancery, County of Suffolk, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1889 January 16 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1892 December 14 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1893 December 11 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
      Certificate appointing DHC as a member of the Board of Trustees of the Hospital Cottages for Children, Boston, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1894 March 15 (Offsite-box Ovz-1)
    - Commissions, 1899 January 12 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Certificate appointing DHC as a member of the Board of Trustess of the Hospital Cottages for Children, Boston, Massachusetts.
    - Commissions, 1899 December 6 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
    - Commissions, 1906 November 28 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
    - Correspondence, 1927 January 27 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Letter from John J. O'Conner to Charles A. Coolidge Sr. thanking him for being an excellent landlord during O'Conner's 50+ years as tenant, Boston, Massachusetts.
    - Legal Briefs, 1873? (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 1)
      Re: dispersal of trusts and property of Samuel A. Shurtleff. Subsequent legal dispute between siblings over bequest. Augustine Shurtleff, complainant; Helen S. Francis and Isabella S. Coolidge, defendants.
    - Correspondence, 1838 December 18 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Letter from Amelia J. Behn in New Orleans, Louisiana, to Mrs. M. Cooke in St. Louis, Missouri (her mother/mother-in-law?). Life in New Orleans: clothing, politics.
    - Correspondence, 1838 December 27 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Letter from Fanny in New Orleans, Louisiana, to her grandmother, V. M. Cooke, in St. Louis, Missouri. Social news at Christmas time.
    - Correspondence, 1839 March 31 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Letter from Amelia J. Behn in New Orleans, Louisiana, to Mrs. M. C. Cooke in St. Louis, Missouri (her mother/mother-in-law?). Social news, including that her sister Caroline is dangerously ill. Mentions Mr. Clapp.
    - Correspondence, 1850 July 15-17 (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 2)
      Thank-you letter for silver inkstand presented to E. S. Dixwell, principal of Boston Latin School, from David H. Coolidge Sr., upon graduation.
    - Correspondence, 1858 December 23-1898 June 12 (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 3)
      Correspondence to David H. Coolidge Sr. and Isabella S. Coolidge from David H. Coolidge Jr. Trip with wife Harriet & daughter Constance to the Caribbean. Details wife's extravagence. 6/12/1898 letter re: marital problems. Silk menu.
    - Scrapbook I (part 1 of 8), circa 1848-1905 (Offsite-box Mem-1)
      Cover and blank pages.
    - Scrapbook I (part 2 of 8), 1848-1862 (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 4)
      Pages containing Boston news clip inc. Ded. of Gettysburg Nat. Cemetery; DHC and George S. Hale creators of electric exhibition. Cert. of safe passage in Civil War South for DHC and R. C. Billings.
    - Scrapbook I (part 3 of 8), 1828 January 30-1865 May 12 (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 5)
      Misc. loose docs. Public Latin School and Harvard College programs. Public speaking text, 1850. Trial of U. H. Crocker. Corr. from James Walker re: Harvard protocol. Lincoln news clip, eulogy & poem. Valentine.
    - Scrapbook I (part 4 of 8), 1869 February 12-1899 February 22 (Offsite-box Man-1, Folder 6)
      Misc. loose docs, mainly social corr. & programs. Corr. DHC re: betrothal of Harrist S. Crowninshield & Elizabeth Sprague to DHC sons (poignant Sprague letter). Thank-you note from newlywed cousin, Mary Moyer.
    - Scrapbook I (part 5 of 8), circa 1870-1890 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 1)
      Misc. loose docs, inc. social corr.; ticket request from O. W. Holmes; letter of thanks and gratitude to DHC from retiring business colleague Chandler; thank-you note from Elizabth S. Coolidge; DHC Republican ticket.
    - Scrapbook I (part 6 of 8), 1900 March 7-1904 July 4 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 2)
      Misc. loose docs, programs and news clips; Charles A. Coolidge Sr. French Legion of Honor; Bar Assoc. program; MA Sons of Amer. Rev. program; Abby Jaquith letter; Constance Coolidge Algeria postcard; DHC jockey photo.
    - Scrapbook I (part 7 of 8), 1852-1903 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Miscellaneous loose news clippings.
    - Scrapbook I (part 8 of 8), 1852-1905 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 3)
      Misc. loose news clip; social & civic news; poems. Inc. Caspar Crowninshield & P. J. McPhall marriage; Boston Mem. Assoc. closes for subway construction; Elizabeth S. Coolidge piano recital.
    - Scrapbook II (part 1 of 2), 1865 June 3-1877 June 27 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 4)
      Whole scrapbook and misc. loose news clips & flyers (Bsoton) re: social and civic events, inc. civic fundraising; Samuel S. Shurtleff lawsuit; Mason-Dixon line; loose printed poems; letter from John Hunti to sister Martha?, 1866.
    - Scrapbook II (part 2 of 2), 1864-1867 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Miscellaneous loose news clippings and 1872 map of Boston.
    - Scrapbook III (part 1 of 26), 1889-1894 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Cover and pages.
    - Scrapbook III (part 2 of 26), 1837 March 8-1860 March 16 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 5)
      Loose copy of will and codicil of David Hill. Abstracts of will of Jonas Coolidge. (David Hill and Jonas Coolidge were the grandfathers of David Hill Coolidge Sr.)
    - Scrapbook III (part 3 of 26), 1842 January 1-1894 December 28 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 6)
      Misc. loose social corr. and Christmas thank-you letters to DHC from family and friends, inc. parental letters advocating good behavior; A. A. Sprague letter in praise of future daughter-in-law Isabella C. Councilman.
    - Scrapbook III (part 4 of 26), 1875 December 29-1876 May 4 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 7)
      Loose corr. to David H. Coolidge Sr. from congressman W. W. Warren. Life as a congressman in D.C., inc. currency and gold standard, impeachment, corruption, and electioneering.
    - Scrapbook III (part 5 of 26), 1897 March 6-1900 April 13 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 8)
      Misc. loose social corr. and thank-you letters to DHC from family and friends, inc. Harriet C. Coolidge in Bermuda; Julia S. Coolidge as new daughter-in-law; Robert C. Billings; Severe fire damage to A. A. Sprague business.
    - Scrapbook III (part 6 of 26), 1844-1890 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 9)
      Misc. loose printed materials, inc. v. small student publication; Frederic S. Coolidge patient appt. card; list of pupils who presented bible to teacher; menu; pharmaceutical co. product brochure; valentine.
    - Scrapbook III (part 7 of 26), circa 1850s (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 10)
      Loose tiny notebook detailing scholastic record of David H. Coolidge Sr. at Harvard University.
    - Scrapbook III (part 8 of 26), circa 1880-1893 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 11)
      Loose printed and handwritten verses, inc. poem to David H. Coolidge Jr. on his 17th birthday, with miniature photographs attached.
    - Scrapbook III (part 9 of 26), 1869 June 19-1900 June 28 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 12)
      Misc. loose programs; flyers; invitation for Boston social events; inc. Elizabeth S. Coolidge concert; George W. Sumner in-memoriam concert; Bar Assoc. dinner; E. E. Hale 70th birthday banquet; Harvard University program.
    - Scrapbook III (part 10 of 26), 1875 October (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 13)
      Loose reprint from American Law Review by Uriel H. Crocker. Empty envelope annotated "Letter of my father C. L. Coolidge to John G. Lock"?
    - Scrapbook III (part 11 of 26), 1884 June-1887 June (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 14)
      Loose Harvard University curricula; class day invitations and program.
    - Scrapbook III (part 12 of 26), 1889-1893 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 15)
      Arlington Street Church programs.
    - Scrapbook III (part 13 of 26), 1891 November 12-1899 October 11 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 16)
      Loose wedding invitations re: Isabella C. Councilman; William T. Councilman; Elizabeth S. Coolidge; Frederic S. Coolidge; Elsie W. Francis; Carleton S. Francis; Mary K. Lathey; Myron A. Lathey.
    - Scrapbook III (part 14 of 26), 1896 October 19-1900 September 26 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 17)
      Loose programs and membership certificate from the Massacusetts Society of the Sons of the American Revolution.
    - Scrapbook III (part 15 of 26), 1897 October 14-15 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 18)
      Loose materials re: death of General Francis Amasa Walker, inc. invitation and newspaper obituary.
    - Scrapbook III (part 16 of 26), 1900 February 22-23 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 19)
      Loose materials re: Massacusetts Society of the Cincinnati, inc. letter approving DHC membership, program, newsclipping.
    - Scrapbook III (part 17 of 26), 1873 February 11-1901 September 27 (Offsite-box Man-2, Folder 20)
      Misc. loose news clip re: family events, inc.: Samuel A. Shurtleff, Frederic S. Coolidge, Mary H. Coolidge, George H. Francis, Hiram S. Shurtleff, Benjamin Shurtleff, Isabela C. Councilman, Edward J. Hill, C. Crowninshield.
    - Scrapbook III (part 18 of 26), 1890-1895 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 1)
      Loose newsclippings re: architecture, inc. architectural designs of Shepley, Rutan & Coolidge for Chicago Art Institute and Chicago Public Library.
    - Scrapbook III (part 19 of 26), circa 1840s-1890s (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 2)
      Loose newsclippings of poetry.
    - Scrapbook III (part 20 of 26), circa 1880-1901 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 3)
      Loose newsclippings of obituaries and weddings (alphabetical order by person), inc. John C. Bancroft, Robert C. Billings, Peleg Chandler, Oliver Ditson, Charles D. Homans, Lucy W. Jaquith, Jonathan A. Lane, Daniel w. Salisbury.
    - Scrapbook III (part 21 of 26), circa 1890s (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 4)
      Loose newsclippings re: wealthy Bostonians.
    - Scrapbook III (part 22 of 26), circa 1880-1900 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 5)
      Loose newsclippings re: individuals in the news.
    - Scrapbook III (part 23 of 26), circa 1880-1900 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 6)
      Loose newsclippings re: general news/items of interest.
    - Scrapbook III (part 24 of 26), 1883-1900 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Miscellaneous loose news clippings (oversize).
    - Scrapbook III (part 25 of 26), circa 1880-1900 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 7)
      Loose newsclippings re: pastors of Arlington Street Unitarian Church.
    - Scrapbook III (part 26 of 26), circa 1890s (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 8)
      Loose newsclippings re: disabled steamship Pavonia; legal claims re: accident.
    - Scrapbook IV, circa 1909? (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 9)
      Small notebook/scrapbook containing newsclippings re: area of Boston and building where he (David H. Coolidge Sr.) was born.
    - Diary, 1865 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 10)
      Entries re: death of Abraham Lincoln.
    - Diary, 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-3)
      Boston. Entries re: weather reports and appointments.
    - Diary, 1899 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-4)
    - Diary, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-5)
    - Diary, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-6)
    - Diary, 1902 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-7)
    - Diary, 1903 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-8)
    - Diary, 1904 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-9)
    - Diary, 1905 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-10)
    - Diary, 1907 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-11)
    - Harvard University, 1866, 1885 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 11)
      Harvard University catalog, 1866; Harvard University publication: Beta Psi Quarterly, 1885.
    - Harvard University, 1886 April 21 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 12)
      Harvard University card to Frederic S. Coolidge. Notice that the university faculty object to reading in Chapel.
    - Chicago World's Fair catalog, 1892 (Offsite-box 1, Box Mem-2)
      Publication of the 1892 World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago.
    - Harvard University, 1894 June 27 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 13)
      Harvard University card to David H. Coolidge Sr., acknowledging receipt of yearbook for Class of 1854. Gift to library.
    - Bostonian Society, 1902 January 13 (Offsite-box Ovz-2)
      Certificate electing David H. Coolidge Sr. as a life member of the Bostonian Society.
    - Society of the Cincinnati, 1923 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 14)
      Society of the Cincinnati membership roster.
    - Carleton family, circa 1840-1900 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 15)
      News clippings.
    - Cooke family, circa 1896 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 16)
    - Coolidge family, circa 1907-1908 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 17)
      News clippings. Includes notation of what might be David H. Coolidge Sr.'s assets at his time of death.
    - Shurtleff family, circa 1856-1891 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 18)
      News clippings. Includes a description of Dr. Benjamin Shurtleff's home in Shasta, California, March 15, 1856.
    - News clippings, 1851-1898 (Offsite-box Man-3, Folder 19)
      Miscellaneous press clippings, including genealogy.
    - Lithograph of a Roma piazza, 1849 (Offsite-box Ovz-4 (cylinder))
  - Subseries I.B. Mary Coolidge Rentschler (1892–1988) [MCR]
    Mary Shepley Coolidge Atkins Rentschler amassed an extraordinary wealth of family materials during her lifetime. Subseries I.B materials include copies of wills, correspondence, diaries, publications, drawings, memorabilia, blueprints, photographic albums, and photographic prints and negatives. The bulk of the written material falls into five main categories: early correspondence and documents, including love letters from Charles A. Coolidge to Julia S. Coolidge (1874–1900); diaries and correspondence from Mary's youth and marriage to Edwin F. Atkins, Jr. (1904–1923); general correspondence and love letters between Mary C. Rentschler and Gordon S. Rentschler (1923–1927); general correspondence to and from Mary C. Rentschler (1927–1974); genealogical material.
    Correspondence, 1874–1900
    In October 1889 Charles A. Coolidge married the sister of George Foster Shepley, one of the original partners of the architectural firm of Shepley Rutan and Coolidge. The love letters from Charles A. Coolidge to Julia Shepley written from February to April 1889 provide insight into a passionate and creative man and a leader in the field of architectural design.
    His passion for art and architecture runs through the correspondence. He read Burkhardt and books about the Italian Renaissance over American literature (1889 March 20; Box Man-4, Folder 1), and describes sketching a Turner painting hanging opposite his bed (1889 March 15; Box Man-3, Folder 22). his firm was busy with many architectural commissions, including the Ames building (the first skyscraper in Boston), and Boston's Trinity Church: "I am going to take up the porch and front of Trinity Church and see if I cannot put it through as I do not know of anything that would be more of an improvement to the City" (1889 April 5; Box Man-4, Folder 1); and Stanford University in California "I spent all day with the Governor and Mrs. Stanford and I think we have finally settled the dormitory. Mrs. S. wanted to talk about you & the engagement & kept interrupting the business talk; you would have been amused and angry at the same time.. ." (1889 April 7; Box Man-4, Folder 1).
    In another letter he writes "Mr. Olmsted telegraphed me today that the Governor will be here" (1889 April 3; Box Man-4, Folder 1). This was, perhaps, Frederick Law Olmsted. The letters suggest a lack of bureaucracy surrounding the construction of so many important buildings, and reflect Coolidge's pivotal involvement in creating the urban landscape of his day.
    His letters are filled with yearning for Julia and a desire for a meaningful relationship (1889 February 27; Box Man-3, Folder 22; and 1889 March 19; Box Man-4, Folder 1). The letters convey an enormous respect, however their passion is not colored by sentimentality. On the contrary, it is the straightforward, almost "modern" quality of the correspondence that is most striking. Although we do not have Julia's letters, the responses in his letters suggest that she is less certain of marriage than he is. In a reply as to whether or not he would take care of her in her old age he says of course, and "as for your having always hated the idea of passing long, long years with one person, I should think that was an argument why you should now make up your mind to leave your mother" (1889 April 3; Box Man-4, Folder 1). He morbidly jokes that with all the traveling he makes to visit her she will soon have her freedom as a young widow, implying that he will die of exhaustion. In another letter he writes "cheer up dear you are not [to] be married yet never if you do not want to be and you need not be married for 'all your life' as you can kill me off very easily afterwards if you want to. Saturday Eve" (1889 circa April 5; Box Man-4, Folder 1).
    This candid attitude reverberates throughout his letters. He is forthright in his dismissal of frivolous socializing and heaps scorn on the temperance movement:
    "I have been holding forth on the false name and position of these temperance people, in the first place no sensible person can help acknowledging that temperance means a moderate & uninjurious use of whatever food or liquid that you may be discussing & when a total abolitionist objects to be called that & says he is simply promoting temperance I feel like telling him he is a liar" (1889 April 8; Box Man-4, Folder 1).
    Correspondence, 1904–1923
    The second group of documents amongst the Mary C. Rentschler material is the diaries and correspondence of her youth and first marriage to Edwin F. Atkins, Jr. (1904–1923). Mary C. Rentschler's diaries span from 1904–1917 (from twelve to twenty-five years of age). Covering her childhood in Jamaica Plain, Massachusetts, to her life in Cuba as a young bride, they provide a glimpse of Boston's youthful high society in 1915 and the life of a young bride and expatriate in Cuba two years later. In 1917 her husband joined the signal corps preparing for action in World War I France. The letters from the soldier to his parents as well as from Mary to her mother-in-law provide descriptions of army life. Finally, the death of Edwin F. Atkins, Jr. and the two sons is recorded in condolence letters to Charles A. Coolidge, Sr. in 1923.